Guide to the New York City COVID-19 Web Activism Collection TAM.798
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York City COVID-19 Web Activism Collection
May 2020-ongoing
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Free Them All for Public Health
Fund Excluded Workers Coalition
NoBody Is Disposable Coalition
COVID Bail Out NYC
Beyond Prisons
DRUM (Organization)
Smalls, Chris
Audre Lorde Project
Krongelb, Malana
Betancourt Macias Family Scholarship Foundation
Butterfly: Asian and Migrant Sex Workers Support Network
Maggie's Toronto Sex Workers Action Project
Corona Courier
Cosecha
Democratic Socialists of America
Dollar Bail Brigade
Freelance Solidarity Project
Herbalista
Housing Justice for All
Hunter College. New York City Food Policy Center
Justice Committee
Kwon, Tre
Make the Road (New York)
Metrowest Worker Center
Movement of Rank and File Educators
Mutual Aid NYC
National Harm Reduction Coalition
New York City COVID-19 Action
New York Immigration Coalition
NYC Covid Care Network
NYC United Against Coronavirus
NYC Veterans Alliance
Piepzna-Samarasinha, Leah Lakshmi, 1975-
Public Power Coalition
Queens Neighborhoods United
Rent Strike 2020
Right to Counsel NYC Coalition
Sex Workers Outreach Project Brooklyn
Talen, Bill
International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America. Joint Council No. 16 (New York, N.Y.)
West Side Federation for Senior Housing
Workers Need Childcare
Gonzalez, Yessica
TAM.798
88 websites in 88 archived websites
The NYC COVID-19 Web Activism Collection, assembled by Tamiment archivists, documents activism and mutual aid in response to the COVID-19 pandemic, starting in 2020. The collection consists of archived websites on topics such as tenants rights, workers organizing surrounding unsafe working conditions, racism, and decarceration.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
Google drive domains (drive.google.com) were partially captured but cannot be played back in Wayback. Instagram pages were captured using Webrecorder, but cannot be played back in Wayback.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Websites are selected by curators Shannon O'Neill and Michael Koncewicz and web archivist Nicole Greenhouse through the use of Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. The accession numbers associated with these websites are 2020.040, 2021.002, 2021.003, 2021.005, 2021.007, 2021.012, 2021.016, 2021.047, 2021.051, 2021.067, 2021.084, 2022.006, 2022.023, 2022.032, 2022.033, 2022.034, and 2022.035
Scope and Contents
The NYC COVID-19 Web Activism Collection documents activists' use of social media and the internet to create content, online campaigns, online actions, virtual mutual aid networks and funds to highlight, resist, and call attention to ways in which COVID-19 has impacted New York City physically, emotionally, politically, and economically. This collection also focused on the ways in which this activism names and addresses the ways in which COVID-19 has disproportionately affected low income communities of color in New York City. Subjects covered within the scope of this collection include organizing around tenants rights and rent strikes; housing insecurity; decarceration campaigns and efforts to raise bail for incarcerated individuals (especially those facing COVID-19 outbreaks in New York City jails); efforts to confront and combat anti-Asian racism; demilitarization campaigns; efforts to confront and combat environmental racism; organizing around access to healthcare; neighborhood autonomy and agency; and support and organizing for workers who are striking against unsafe work conditions, lack of hazard pay, and/or lack of benefits. This is an artificial collection, materials were selected by Tamiment curators and arranged by an archivist.
Arrangement
Websites are arranged alphabetically by creator.
Conditions Governing Access
Majority of the collection is open to researchers without restrictions. Some materials are closed to protect the privacy of activists.
Historical Note
In March 2020, non-essential businesses throughout New York City closed in an effort to contain COVID-19, a respiratory virus that first identified in December 2019. The virus and the closures disproportionally affected systematically excluded groups. Within days of the shutdown, activists began to organize to provide mutual aid and information about the COVID-19 to support sex workers, veterans, immigrants, LGBTQIA people, incarcerated people, workers, and others. Over the course of the pandemic, these individuals and organizations pushed for worker protections, housing and tenant relief, decarceration, and called attention to ways in which COVID-19 has impacted New York City physically, emotionally, politically, and economically. During the pandemic, George Floyd, a black man, was killed by Derek Chauvin, a white police officer, in May 2020. This led to protests calling for the abolishment of the police and a resurgence in the Black Lives Matter movement. As the pandemic continued into 2021 and 2022, pushes for a "return to normal" by the establishment and government--despite continued resurgences in COVID-19 cases and deaths--led to activists pushing for rent assistance, an eviction moratorium, vaccine mandates, masking, ventilation and other environmental concerns, unionization efforts, city budget reforms, safe staffing for healthcare workers, and more permanent actions to keep people safe and healthy. As of this writing in April 2022, the pandemic is still an active part of life.
Appraisal
Robots.txt (a piece of code designed to limit crawler activity within a website) was ignored. The collection was rescoped to allow for Google documents, videos, and Airtable forms embedded in the website.
COVID-19 (Disease); Housing -- Law and legislation.; Undocumented Immigrants; Street vendors; Nurses -- Labor unions -- United States.; Sex workers; Harm reduction; Prison abolition movements; Truck drivers -- Labor unions -- United States.; Strikes and lockouts -- United States.
- The Audre Lorde Project, May 2020-February 2022; Audre Lorde Project (Box Electronic Records)
  Scope and Contents
  The Audre Lorde Project (ALP) is a Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Two Spirit, Trans and Gender Nonconforming (LGBTSTGNC) People of Color center for community organizing in New York City. ALP works for progressive social and economic justice and the promotion of community wellness. The ALP "Know Your Housing Rights During COVID-19" guide was written by Kerbie Joseph, ALP's Safe Outside the System Coordinator. It provides tenants rights information around eviction, rent demands from landlords, utility shut-offs, and shares strategies for collective tenant organizing.
- COVID-19 Resources for Undocumented Immigrants, June 2020-February 2022; Betancourt Macias Family Scholarship Foundation (Box Electronic Records)
  Google document linked from the SWOP Brooklyn website's COVID resource page listing financial, medical, mutual aid, food, and legal resources for undocumented immigrants organized by state.
- Beyond Prisons Prisoner Support Guide the Coronavirus Crisis, May-June 2020; Beyond Prisons (Box Electronic Records)
  Document linked from the SWOP Brooklyn website's COVID resource page describing best practices on supporting incarcerated people during the COVID-19 pandemic.
- Sex Work and COVID-19: Guidelines for Sex Workers, Clients, Third Parties, and Allies, June 2020-February 2022; Butterfly: Asian and Migrant Sex Workers Support Network; Maggie's Toronto Sex Workers Action Project (Box Electronic Records)
  Document linked from the SWOP Brooklyn website's COVID resource page describing protective guidelines for sex workers, clients, third parties, and allies.
- Corona Courier, June 2020-March 2021 (Box Electronic Records)
  Corona Courier is a mutual-aid group of NYC cyclists who provide free no-contact delivery service to most at-risk community members during the COVID-19 public health crisis. They have around 450 volunteers located across Manhattan, Brooklyn, Queens and The Bronx. Along with general courier work, they help with grocery shopping and food assistance in Brooklyn, Manhattan and Queens. In The Bronx they are currently partnering with Montefiore Hospital and BXMpowerment Project to help with their pantry deliveries.
- Undocumented Worker Fund, May 2020-February 2022; Cosecha (Box Electronic Records)
  Cosecha is "a nonviolent movement fighting for permanent protection, dignity, and respect for the 11 million undocumented immigrants in the United States." In response to the COVID-19 crisis, Cosecha established an undocumented workers fund campaign, encouraging individuals to donate their federal government stimulus checks to support undocumented workers who were excluded from participation in the stimulus check program.
- How Movimiento Cosecha operates a COVID-19 fund by and for undocumented immigrants, February 2022; Cosecha (Box Electronic Records)
  Blog post from Cosecha detailing how funds were used from the undocumented workers fund.
- Nos Cuida La Comunidad: Cosecha's COVID-19 Fund for Undocumented Workers has Redistributed $1 Million, February 2022; Cosecha (Box Electronic Records)
- Bail Payer Volunteer Sign-Up, June 2020-ongoing; COVID Bail Out NYC (Box Electronic Records)
  Google form for bail payer volunteer sign-up.
- COVID Bail Out NYC Attorney/Social Worker Requests, January 2022-ongoing; COVID Bail Out NYC (Box Electronic Records)
  Google form for attorney and/or social worker requests.
- COVID Bail Out NYC Community Requests, August 2020-ongoing; COVID Bail Out NYC (Box Electronic Records)
  Google form for requests for bail out.
- COVID Bail Out NYC, May 2020-ongoing (Box Electronic Records)
  COVID Bail Out NYC is a volunteer, emergency grassroots initiative partnering with Emergency Release Fund and Black Alliance for Just Immigration to support bailing incarcerated people from Rikers Island Prison and in New York City jails. COVID Bail-Out NYC centralizes funding to post bail, provide support to public defenders, and providing post-release support. Through the website, individuals can donate funding and volunteer to post bail. It also calls for trained social workers, mediators, healers, and individuals trained in conflict resolution to volunteer time to support individuals upon their release from prison or jail. The website also allows for attorneys to make referrals for incarcerated individuals who need to post bail. The website also includes a semi-regularly updated Instagram feed for @covidbailoutnyc which includes update posts on the number of individual who have been released from prison or jail due to the initiative.
- We Need a COVID-19 Response that Put People before Profit Petition, May 2020-February 2022; Democratic Socialists of America (Box Electronic Records)
  Petition linked from the New York City COVID-19 action campaign list. Petition on Medicare for All, worker protection, safe housing, and debt forgiveness.
- We Need a People's Bailout for New York! Petition, May 2020-February 2022; Democratic Socialists of America (Box Electronic Records)
  Petition linked from the New York City COVID-19 action campaign list. Petition on making COVID-19 testing and treatment free, protecting Medicaid, keeping workers safe and secure, and other issues.
- Dollar Bail Brigade Volunteer Guide, May 2020-February 2022; Dollar Bail Brigade (Box Electronic Records)
  Guide linked from the Free Them All for Public Health website on how to bail out people in New York City jails.
- Building Power & Safety Through Solidarity, May 2020-July 2021; DRUM (Organization) (Box Electronic Records)
  DRUM - Desis Rising Up and Moving is a multigenerational, membership led organization of low-wage South Asian and Indo-Caribbean immigrant workers and youth in New York City. Founded in 2000, DRUM's membership of over 3,000 adults, youth, and families is multigenerational and represents the diaspora of the South Asian communities – Afghanistan, Bangladesh, Bhutan, Guyana, India, Nepal, Pakistan, Sri Lanka, Suriname, Trinidad & Tobago, and beyond. In over a decade, they have built a model of South Asian and Indo-Caribbean undocumented workers, women, and youth led organizing for rights and justice from the local to the global. Their long-term vision is to build the power of immigrant workers in the U.S in unity with all workers and communities for human rights. They see movements for justice in the U.S. as rooted in working in solidarity with people of the Global South for just global trade, economic, and foreign policies. Their Power and Safety website includes community resources, a community-organizing toolkit, community mutual aid funds, and testimonials documenting community members' experiences during COVID-19.
- #FTA4PH Partner Org Resource Survey, May 2020-February 2022; Free Them All for Public Health (Box Electronic Records)
  Google form surveying for resources in the Free Them All for Public Health community.
- #FTA4PH Phone Bank Resource Survey, May 2020-February 2022; Free Them All for Public Health (Box Electronic Records)
  Google form for a phone bank resource survey in the Free Them All for Public Health community.
- Abolish NYPD-Close Rikers Graphics, July 2020-February 2022; Free Them All for Public Health (Box Electronic Records)
  Graphics on calls for abolishing the New York Police Department and closing the Rikers Island jail.
- Abolitionist Recommendations to Defund NYPD, with No New Jails by Closing Rikers Now, July 2020-February 2022; Free Them All for Public Health (Box Electronic Records)
  Pamphlet calling to abolish the New York Police Department and the closing of the Rikers Island jail by rellocating the budget for the 2021 fiscal year.
- Budget Release Talking Points, July 2020-February 2022; Free Them All for Public Health (Box Electronic Records)
  Google document containing example tweets related to the defunding the police and closing the Rikers Island jail.
- Free People from Jail, May 2020-February 2022; Free Them All for Public Health (Box Electronic Records)
  Google document calling for the release of incarcerated people from New York City jails.
- Free Them All for Public Health, May 2020-July 2021 (Box Electronic Records)
  Free them All for Public Health, or #freethemall4publichealth, is a campaign that demands the release of incarcerated people. The campaign recognizes a longer-term goal of abolition; however, it calls for immediate reductions of prosecution, probation, and court monitoring; the release of people from jails; and the release of people from prisons as measures of reducing the spread of COVID-19. The campaign calls upon individuals to participate in "zaps," actions in which elected officials, and individuals associated with the Department of Corrections, are contacted en masse through phone calls, faxes, emails, and social media. This website documents not only the demands of Free Them All, but the demands of incarcerated people at three city jails. It also lists actions, provides resources on decarceration and abolition, and links to recent news related to COVID-19 and incarceration. #freethemall4publichealth is a parallel campaign with #CloseRikersNOW.
- Free Them All 4 Public Health Virtual Phone Banking Training Document, May 2020-February 2022; Free Them All for Public Health (Box Electronic Records)
  Google document on training for virtual phone banking to free incarcerated people from jails.
- PUBLIC FTA4PH Outreach Toolkit, May 2020-July 2021; Free Them All for Public Health (Box Electronic Records)
  Outreach toolkit for the Free Them All for Public Health campaign.
- Reduce Criminalization, May 2020-February 2022; Free Them All for Public Health (Box Electronic Records)
  Google document on decreasing criminalization in New York State.
- Response to New York City's 2020 Budget, June 2020-February 2022; Free Them All for Public Health (Box Electronic Records)
  Google document on Free Them All for Public Health's response to the 2020 New York City budget.
- Sample Script for COVID-19 Phone Banking, May 2020-February 2022; Free Them All for Public Health (Box Electronic Records)
  Google document containing a sample script for COVID-19 phone banking for the release of incarcerated people.
- Tips for Phone Banking, May 2020-February 2022; Free Them All for Public Health (Box Electronic Records)
  Google document for tips for phone banking for the release of incarcerated people.
- Freelance Solidarity Project – Emergency Resource Guide, May 2020-February 2022; Freelance Solidarity Project (Box Electronic Records)
  Resource list linked from the New York City COVID-19 action campaign list. Organized by New York City neighborhood.
- #FundExcludedWorkers, November 2021-ongoing; Fund Excluded Workers Coalition (Box Electronic Records)
  The Fund Excluded Workers (FEW) Coalition is a coalition of labor and activist groups demanding covid relief funding for undocumented workers and those who have recently been released from incarceration, both of whom are being excluded from relief packages. Their campaign calls for the creation of an Excluded Worker Fund, develop through a tax on the wealthy, to "provide direct income support, equivalent to unemployment benefits." On March 16th, 2021, members of the coalition began a hunger strike demanding that legislators in Albany fund excluded workers, which led to a $2.1 billion Excluded Workers Fund.. In March 2022, the coalition marched to Albany to promote their platform that called for $3 billion to replenish the Exclude Workers Fund, street vendor legalization, health coverage for all, fair wages, and worker protections.
- #FundExcludedWorkers Hunger Strike, December 2021-February 2022; Fund Excluded Workers Coalition (Box Electronic Records)
  In March-April 2021, excluded workers went on a 23-day hunger strike to demand that legislators in Albany fund excluded workers. On April, the strike ended when the Excluded Workers Fund was passed. This website consists of a playlists of videos from the strike.
- Mask Making Zine, June 2020-February 2022; Gonzalez, Yessica (Box Electronic Records)
  Google document linked from the SWOP Brooklyn website's COVID resource page and contains directions on how to make a mask.
- COVID-19 Community Care Guide, June 2020-February 2022; Herbalista (Box Electronic Records)
  Google document linked from the SWOP Brooklyn website's COVID resource page. Practical resources and protocols for community herbalists related to COVID-19.
- Eviction Free NY, May 2021-ongoing; Housing Justice for All (Box Electronic Records)
  Tool created by Right to Counsel NYC Coalition, Housing Justice for All, and JustFix.nyc to assist New York tenants facing hardship due to COVID-19 health risks or lost income to protect from eviction.
- Housing Justice for All, June 2020-ongoing (Box Electronic Records)
  Housing Justice for All is a campaign initiated by Upstate/Downstate Housing Alliance. The Alliance is a coalition that seeks to end evictions, end homelessness, and fights for stronger tenant protections. The website contains reports related to rent striking, renters rights, homelessness, and housing unaffordability. The website contains news related to their work on housing insecurity exacerbated by the COVID-19 pandemic.
- Housing Justice For All -- COVID-19 Response, Petition, and Pledge, May 2020-April 2021; Housing Justice for All (Box Electronic Records)
  Housing Justice for All is a campaign initiated by Upstate/Downstate Housing Alliance. The Alliance is a coalition that seeks to end evictions, end homelessness, and fights for stronger tenant protections. The Housing Justice for All website includes links to tenants rights information, links to a bilingual rent strike toolkit (Spanish and English), a map of tenant stories from across the state of New York, a petition, and pledge to join the May 1st rent strike. The Reclaim Our Homes petition is a call to suspend rent and mortgages in New York during the COVID-19 crisis.The petition is sponsored by the Upstate/Downstate Housing Alliance along with twenty-six co-sponsored from various social justice, activist, and housing justice organizations across the New York City and the state of New York. The petition is bilingual (Spanish and English) and links to a Google doc version of the petition that is translated into Chinese. The pledge is translated into four languages including Bangla, Korean, Chinese, and English, and it seeks to build a mass movement of rent strikers beginning in May. It aims to have 6,400 individuals join the pledge.
- Housing Justice For All Twitter, May 2020-ongoing; Housing Justice for All (Box Electronic Records)
  Housing Justice for All is a campaign initiated by Upstate/Downstate Housing Alliance. The Alliance is a coalition that seeks to end evictions, end homelessness, and fights for stronger tenant protections. On March 11, 2020, the Housing Justice for All Twitter feed focuses on housing justice responses to COVID-19 including calls for moratorium on evictions and suspensions of rents and mortgages. The feed includes use of the #CancelRent, #CantPayMay, #HomelessCantStayHome, #ReclaimOurHomes, and #RentStrike hashtag campaigns, and is inclusive of testimonies from tenants across New York as they navigate housing inequality across the state.
- Reclaim Our Homes: Rent/Mortgage Suspension Now! Petition, May-February 2022; Housing Justice for All (Box Electronic Records)
  Petition to create permanent housing for homeless New Yorkers.